Andrew Casey-Clyde

Research Assistant, Ph.D. Physics

Saratoga, CA
☐ +1 (408) 691 2718
☑ jacaseyclyde@gmail.com
⑤ jacaseyclyde.github.io
in jacaseyclyde
⑤ jacaseyclyde



Summary

Ph.D. Research Assistant with 8+ years of data analysis, modeling, and research experience in astrophysics. Lead author of 3 research papers, including for a collaboration of 100+ scientists. Co-author of 17+ research papers and two white papers. Presented novel research at 27+ scientific meetings, conferences, and seminars. Gave 5 general public talks for non-technical audiences.

Experience

2023-present Visiting Research Assistant, Yale University, New Haven, CT

Analyzing astrophysical data to model supermassive black hole binary (SMBHB) populations.

- Led gravitational wave data analysis and modeling project for collaboration of 100+ scientists.
- O Developed Bayesian, data-driven models of individual SMBHBs and SMBHB populations.
- o Simulated 1000 SMBHB populations and their gravitational wave signals to interpret observed data.
- 2019-present **Graduate Research and Teaching Assistant**, *University of Connecticut*, Storrs, CT Developed data-driven models of SMBHB populations.
 - Developed three hierarchical Bayesian models of SMBHB populations to predict population properties.
 - O Developed novel statistical method to efficiently sample multivariate probability distributions.
 - 2016–2019 **Graduate Research and Teaching Associate**, San José State University, San Jose, CA Performed astrophysics research and data analysis, and taught undergraduate physics labs.
 - $\,\circ\,$ Developed Bayesian data analysis to model gas observed in the galactic center.
 - 2015–2016 **Software Engineer**, *Salient Process, Inc.*, Sacramento, CA Developed and maintained both internal and client-facing software.

Education

- 2019-2024 Ph.D. Physics, University of Connecticut, Storrs, CT, GPA: 3.823
- 2019–2023 M.S. Physics, University of Connecticut, Storrs, CT
- 2016–2019 M.S. Physics, San José State University, San Jose, CA, GPA: 3.791 Computational concentration
- 2010–2014 **B.S. Physics**, *University of California, Davis*, Davis, CA, *GPA*: 2.945 Astrophysics emphasis

Skills

Core Statistics, data analysis, research Technical Python, SLURM, SQL, git Software Jupyter lab, NumPy, SciPy, PyMC, Visualization Matplotlib, ArviZ, Seaborn

Pandas, Scikit-learn

Communication Scientific writing, science presentation Other Project management, collaboration

Ph.D. Thesis

Title Multi-Messenger Constraints on Supermassive Black Hole Binaries

Advisors Chiara M. F. Mingarelli, Jonathan R. Trump, Daniel Anglès-Alcàzar

Description The nanohertz gravitational wave background (GWB) is thought to be dominated by gravitational waves from supermassive black hole (SMBH) binaries (SMBHBs) - systems of two SMBHs which result from galaxy mergers. Quasars - i.e., bright, accreting SMBHs - have long been associated with galaxy mergers, suggesting a link with SMBHBs. In this work I developed novel models of the SMBHB population using observations of the GWB, quasars, and galaxies. Using these models I found the gravitational wave background implies SMBHBs may be eight times more numerous than previously expected. I further found that guasars may be up to seven times more likely to host a SMBHB than random galaxies. Finally, I found an excursion in the spectrum of the GWB at 16 nHz which is louder than the average expected signal from SMBHBs at $\sim 2\sigma$ confidence.

Master's Thesis

Title Integrated Kinematic Fitting of Gas Streams in the Milky Way's Circumnuclear Disk

Advisors Elisabeth A. C. Mills, Aaron Romanowsky

Description I developed a data-driven model of gas orbiting the supermassive black hole at the center of our galaxy. I used a leapfrog integration scheme to model gas orbits in the center of our galaxy. I then developed a Bayesian analysis pipeline to fit this model to kinematic data for gas observed in the center of our galaxy. I found that the observed gas must pass within $\sim 1.6 \mathrm{pc}$ of our galaxy's central supermassive black hole.

Professional Development

Vanderbilt University

2022 VIPER Summer School on Pulsar Timing Array Gravitational Wave Astrophysics

Niels Bohr International Academy

o 2021 Summer School on Gravitational Wave Astrophysics

Flatiron Institute, Center for Computational Astronomy

Machine Learning

Selected Coursework

University of Connecticut

- Stars and Compact Objects
- General Relativity and Cosmology

Statistical Mechanics

San José State University

Astronomy Data Analysis

- Deep Learning
- O Statistical and Machine Learning Classifica- O Numerical Analysis and Scientific Computing

Computational Physics

Methods in Mathematical Physics

University of California, Davis

 Astronomy Instrumentation & Data Analysis
 Statistics Through Computation Lab

- o Introductory Methods of Mathematical o Computational Methods of Mathematical **Physics**
- Linear Algebra Computation Lab
- o Intro to Programming & Problem Solving
- Physics
- o Discrete Math for Computer Science
- Software & Object Oriented Programming

Publications

Published

- [1] Johnson, Aaron D., [...], **Casey-Clyde, J. Andrew**, et al. May 2024. "NANOGrav 15-Year Gravitational-Wave Background Methods". *Physical Review D* 109, p. 103012.
- [2] Davis, Megan C., [...], **Casey-Clyde, J. Andrew**, et al. Apr. 2024. "Reliable Identification of Binary Supermassive Black Holes from Rubin Observatory Time-domain Monitoring". *The Astrophysical Journal* 965, p. 34.
- [3] Kelley, Luke Zoltan, [...], Casey-Clyde, J. Andrew, et al. Apr. 2024. "Nanograv/Holodeck: V1.5.2". Zenodo.
- [4] Agazie, Gabriella, [...], **Casey-Clyde, J. Andrew**, et al. Mar. 2024. "The NANOGrav 12.5 Yr Data Set: A Computationally Efficient Eccentric Binary Search Pipeline and Constraints on an Eccentric Supermassive Binary Candidate in 3C 66B". *The Astrophysical Journal* 963, p. 144.
- [5] Agazie, Gabriella, [...], **Casey-Clyde, J. Andrew**, et al. Mar. 2024. "The NANOGrav 12.5 Yr Data Set: Search for Gravitational Wave Memory". *The Astrophysical Journal* 963, p. 61.
- [6] Agazie, Gabriella, [...], **Casey-Clyde, J. Andrew**, et al. Mar. 2024. "The NANOGrav 15 Yr Data Set: Search for Transverse Polarization Modes in the Gravitational-wave Background". *The Astrophysical Journal* 964, p. L14.
- [7] Bécsy, Bence, [...], **Casey-Clyde, J. Andrew**, et al. Dec. 2023. "How to Detect an Astrophysical Nanohertz Gravitational Wave Background". *The Astrophysical Journal* 959, p. 9.
- [8] Agazie, Gabriella, [...], **Casey-Clyde, J. Andrew**, et al. Oct. 2023. "The NANOGrav 15 Yr Data Set: Search for Anisotropy in the Gravitational-wave Background". *The Astrophysical Journal* 956, p. L3.
- [9] Khusid, Nicole M., [...], **Casey-Clyde, J. Andrew**, et al. Sept. 2023. "Strongly Lensed Supermassive Black Hole Binaries as Nanohertz Gravitational-wave Sources". *The Astrophysical Journal* 955, p. 25.
- [10] Agazie, Gabriella, [...], Casey-Clyde, J. Andrew, et al. Aug. 2023. "The NANOGrav 15 Yr Data Set: Constraints on Supermassive Black Hole Binaries from the Gravitational-wave Background". The Astrophysical Journal 952, p. L37.
- [11] Agazie, Gabriella, [...], **Casey-Clyde, J. Andrew**, et al. July 2023. "The NANOGrav 15 Yr Data Set: Bayesian Limits on Gravitational Waves from Individual Supermassive Black Hole Binaries". *The Astrophysical Journal* 951, p. L50.
- [12] Arzoumanian, Zaven, [...], **Casey-Clyde, J. Andrew**, et al. July 2023. "The NANOGrav 12.5 Yr Data Set: Bayesian Limits on Gravitational Waves from Individual Supermassive Black Hole Binaries". *The Astrophysical Journal* 951, p. L28.
- [13] Falxa, M., [...], Casey-Clyde, J. A., et al. June 2023. "Searching for Continuous Gravitational Waves in the Second Data Release of the International Pulsar Timing Array". *Monthly Notices of the Royal Astronomical Society* 521, pp. 5077–5086.
- [14] Koss, Michael J., [...], **Casey-Clyde, J. Andrew**, et al. Jan. 2023. "UGC 4211: A Confirmed Dual Active Galactic Nucleus in the Local Universe at 230 Pc Nuclear Separation". *The Astrophysical Journal* 942, p. L24.
- [15] Mingarelli, Chiara M. F. and **Casey-Clyde, J. Andrew**. Nov. 2022. "Seeing the Gravitational Wave Universe". *Science* 378, pp. 592–593.
- [16] Antoniadis, J., [...], **Casey-Clyde, J. A.**, et al. Mar. 2022. "The International Pulsar Timing Array Second Data Release: Search for an Isotropic Gravitational Wave Background". *Monthly Notices of the Royal Astronomical Society* 510, pp. 4873–4887.
- [17] Casey-Clyde, J. Andrew et al. Jan. 2022. "A Quasar-based Supermassive Black Hole Binary Population Model: Implications for the Gravitational Wave Background". *The Astrophysical Journal* 924, p. 93.

Forthcoming

[1] Agazie, Gabriella, [...], **Casey-Clyde, J. Andrew**, et al. July 2024. *The NANOGrav 15 Yr Data Set: Posterior Predictive Checks for Gravitational-Wave Detection with Pulsar Timing Arrays*.

[2] Agazie, Gabriella, [...], Casey-Clyde, J. Andrew, et al. Apr. 2024. The NANOGrav 15 Yr Data Set: Looking for Signs of Discreteness in the Gravitational-wave Background.

Submitted

- [1] Agazie, Gabriella, [...], **Casey-Clyde, J. Andrew**, et al. Nov. 2024. *The NANOGrav 15 Yr Data Set: Harmonic Analysis of the Pulsar Angular Correlations*.
- [2] Chen, Yifan, [...], **Casey-Clyde, J. Andrew**, et al. Nov. 2024. *Galaxy Tomography with the Gravitational Wave Background from Supermassive Black Hole Binaries*.
- [3] Laal, Nima, [...], **Casey-Clyde, J. Andrew**, et al. Nov. 2024. *Deep Neural Emulation of the Supermassive Black-hole Binary Population*.
- [4] Semenzato, Federico, **Casey-Clyde, J. Andrew** et al. Nov. 2024. *Cross-Correlating the Universe: The Gravitational Wave Background and Large-Scale Structure.*
- [5] Agazie, Gabriella, [...], **Casey-Clyde, J. Andrew**, et al. Aug. 2024. *The NANOGrav 15 Yr Data Set: Running of the Spectral Index*.
- [6] Casey-Clyde, J. Andrew et al. May 2024. Quasars Can Signpost Supermassive Black Hole Binaries.

White Papers

- [1] Haiman, Zoltán, [...], **Casey-Clyde, J. Andrew**, et al. June 2023. *Massive Black Hole Binaries as LISA Precursors in the Roman High Latitude Time Domain Survey*.
- [2] Shen, Yue, **Casey-Clyde, J. Andrew** et al. June 2023. *Discovery and Characterization of Galactic-scale Dual Supermassive Black Holes Across Cosmic Time*.

Presentations

Talks

- [1] Casey-Clyde, J. Andrew. Nov. 2024. *Multi-Messenger Constraints on Supermassive Black Hole Binaries*. Dissertation Defense. Storrs, Connecticut.
- [2] Casey-Clyde, J. Andrew. Sept. 2024. Multi-Messenger Constraints on Supermassive Black Hole Binaries. Virtual.
- [3] Casey-Clyde, J. Andrew. Jan. 2024. *Quasars Can Signpost Supermassive Black Hole Binaries*. Contributed Talk. New Orleans, Louisiana.
- [4] Casey-Clyde, J. Andrew. Dec. 2023. Multi-Messenger Constraints on Supermassive Black Hole Binaries. Invited Talk. Pittsburgh, Pennsylvania.
- [5] Casey-Clyde, J. Andrew. Dec. 2023. *Quasars Can Signpost Supermassive Black Hole Binaries*. Contributed Talk. Miami, Florida.
- [6] Casey-Clyde, J. Andrew. Oct. 2023. Interpreting Power-Law Excursions in Nanohertz Gravitational-Wave Background Spectra. Contributed Talk. Vancouver, British Colombia, Canada.
- [7] Casey-Clyde, J. Andrew. July 2023. How Many Quasars Host Supermassive Black Hole Binary Systems? Contributed Talk.
- [8] Casey-Clyde, J. Andrew. June 2023. *How Many Quasars Host SMBHB Systems?* Contributed Talk. Port Douglas, Australia.
- [9] Casey-Clyde, J. Andrew. Mar. 2023. How Many Quasars Host Supermassive Black Hole Binary Systems? Contributed Talk.
- [10] Casey-Clyde, J. Andrew. Mar. 2023. *Interpreting Nanohertz Gravitational-Wave Background Spectra*. Contributed Talk. Corvallis, Oregon.
- [11] Casey-Clyde, J. Andrew. Feb. 2023. How Many Quasars Host Supermassive Black Hole Binaries? Invited Talk. Storrs, Connecticut.
- [12] Casey-Clyde, J. Andrew. Jan. 2023. How Many Quasars Host Supermassive Black Hole Binaries? Contributed Talk. Seattle, Washington.

- [13] Casey-Clyde, J. Andrew. Oct. 2022. How Many Quasars Host Supermassive Black Hole Binaries? Contributed Talk. Milwaukee, Wisconsin.
- [14] Casey-Clyde, J. Andrew. July 2022. Quantifying the Relationship Between Supermassive Black Hole Binaries and Quasars Using Pulsar Timing Arrays. Contributed Talk. Nashville, Tennessee, United States.
- [15] Casey-Clyde, J. Andrew. July 2022. Quantifying the Relationship Between Supermassive Black Hole Binaries and Quasars Using Pulsar Timing Arrays. Contributed Talk.
- [16] Casey-Clyde, J. Andrew. June 2022. A Quasar-Based Supermassive Black Hole Binary Population Model: Implications for the Gravitational-Wave Background. Contributed Talk. Pasadena, California, United States.
- [17] Casey-Clyde, J. Andrew. June 2022. Quantifying the Relationship Between Supermassive Black Hole Binaries and Quasars Using Pulsar Timing Arrays. Contributed Talk.
- [18] Casey-Clyde, J. Andrew. Apr. 2022. A Quasar-Based Supermassive Black Hole Binary Population Model: Implications for the Gravitational-Wave Background. Contributed Talk. New York, New York, United States.
- [19] Casey-Clyde, J. Andrew. Mar. 2022. Quantifying the Relationship Between Supermassive Black Hole Binaries and Quasars Using Pulsar Timing Arrays. Contributed Talk. New York, New York, United States.
- [20] Casey-Clyde, J. Andrew. Dec. 2021. An AGN-based Supermassive Black Hole Binary Population Model: Implications for the Gravitational-Wave Background. Contributed Talk.
- [21] Casey-Clyde, J. Andrew. Sept. 2021. Anchoring Supermassive Black Hole Binaries to Quasars with the Gravitational-Wave Background. Contributed Talk. Center for Computational Astronomy, Flatiron Institute, New York, New York.
- [22] Casey-Clyde, J. Andrew. July 2021. Anchoring Supermassive Black Hole Binaries to Active Galactic Nuclei with the Gravitational-Wave Background. Contributed Talk.
- [23] Casey-Clyde, J. Andrew. June 2021. Anchoring Supermassive Black Hole Binaries to Active Galactic Nuclei with the Gravitational Wave Background. Contributed Talk.
- [24] Casey-Clyde, J. Andrew. Apr. 2021. Interpreting the Gravitational Wave Background in Terms of Supermassive Black Hole Binary Populations. Contributed Talk.
- [25] Casey-Clyde, J. Andrew. Oct. 2020. Interpreting the Gravitational-Wave Background in Terms of Supermassive Black Hole Binary Populations. Contributed Talk.
- [26] Casey-Clyde, J. Andrew. Sept. 2020. Constraining Supermassive Black Hole Binary Populations with PTAs. Contributed Talk.
- [27] Casey-Clyde, J. Andrew. July 2020. Constraining Supermassive Black Hole Binary Populations with PTAs. Invited Talk.

Posters

- [1] Casey-Clyde, J. Andrew. Nov. 2021. A Quasar-Based Model of Supermassive Black Hole Binaries. Poster. Windsor Locks, CT, USA.
- [2] Casey-Clyde, J. Andrew. July 2021. Anchoring Supermassive Black Hole Binaries to Active Galactic Nuclei with the Gravitational-Wave Background. Poster.
- [3] Casey-Clyde, J. Andrew. June 2021. Interpreting the Gravitational Wave Background in Terms of Supermassive Black Hole Binary Populations. Poster.
- [4] Casey-Clyde, J. Andrew. Jan. 2021. Interpreting the Gravitational-Wave Background in Terms of Supermassive Black Hole Binary Populations. iPoster.
- [5] Casey-Clyde, J. Andrew, Thummar, H., and Donet, J. Jan. 2019. *Galaxy Classification with Neural Networks in SDSS*. Seattle, WA, USA.
- [6] Casey-Clyde, J. Andrew. Jan. 2018. Mapping Gas Orbits in the Circumnuclear Disk. Poster. Washington, D.C., USA.
- [7] Casey-Clyde, J. Andrew. Aug. 2017. *Kinematics of the Eastern Arm in the Circumnuclear Disk*. Poster. Quy Nhon, Vietnam.

Outreach

May 2024	Seagrave Observatory , <i>Skyscrapers Amateur Astronomical Society</i> , North Scituate, RI Low Frequency Gravitational Waves: A New View of the Universe
	Hops 44, Astronomy on Tap, Storrs, CT Gravitational Waves and Multi-Messenger Astronomy
August 2023	Hops 44 , Astronomy on Tap, Storrs, CT Supermassive Black Holes: A Crash Course on the Biggest Objects in the Universe
May 2023	Ecotarium , Astrophysical Speaker Series, Worcester, MA Low Frequency Gravitational Waves: A New View of the Universe
January 2022	Connecticut Invention Convention , <i>Virtual Inventors Club</i> , Virtual Provided project mentorship to middle school-age student inventors.